Estimated
expected value right and likewise at the end
to recommend a specific com I also use the
estimated expected, value there is a whole
other class of algorithms that directly work
with the directly work with the, representation
of the policy right so what do I mean by a
policy here, I told you what a policy was
in the very first class right what is the
policy, I sense a mapping from States to actions
or states to action probabilities that in
this case we really have no states right so
for we have not considered any states.
.
So what would a policy be in this case sorry
yeah it could be just one arm or it could
be some kind of a probability distribution
over the arms right it could be one or more
some probability distribution over the arms
so I am going to denote this by right, so
which is the probability of pulling arm A
right and my goal is to keep changing this
policy over time, says that eventually I will
be recommending with probability one to pull
the best arm right.
So this policy is going to keep changing over
time so I am going to denote this way so the
policy is going to keep changing over time
and denote this by pt right, so now what a
learning algorithm has to do in such a case
is it has to give me away of changing this
pt with time right, so one way of thinking
about things like epsilon greedy right or
soft max is that they define this pt in an
indirect fashion right if you remember I wrote
it down also right.
I know I wrote down what pt would be for epsilon
greedy and soft max I started off by writing
in force soft max then it came back and wrote
it down for epsilon greedy right people remember
that I said what will be the probability of
picking I don't know if I use the p notation
that they use the p notation yes, I use P
the probability of picking action race I didn't
because I didn't introduce the p notation
I did not think I used it but essentially
the probability of picking an action I have
written probability at=a right, that is exactly
what pt(a) is right.
So this is, it is a probability that at=a
to this is additional notation we will be
using the notation p throughout right, so
later we will use will condition this on this
states also that lessons the probability that
at=a given st=s right, here since there’s
only one state we do not have to do that great,
so some of the earliest known approaches for
solving bandits use this kind of a direct
policy search right.
.
So some kind of us policy search approach
right so in that what we do is, so let us
let us keep it simple I will talk about a
two action case right and then we can talk
about other things right so the very very
simplified the situation which is called the
binary bandit where there are only two outcomes
either you get a 0 or you get a 1 right, so
is a good outcome 0 is a bad outcome this
just makes me and this is going to give you
like the historic perspective here okay.
So in fact it is so historic that in addition
to they got rid of all of this discussion
in the book, right so if you want to know
more about the kind of things I am talking
about right now we'll have to go back and
read addition one of the RL book, so let us
say I'm talk about binary banditos Rt can
be either 0 or 1 okay, and let us say I have
a two armed bandit case here so I have only
armed one or arm too just to make my thing
easy.
So if right at some time t Rt=1 right, then
what I will do is I will make, p t+1 of at
essentially the action I took at time T right
at is action at took at time T and the reward
I got was 1 so what should I do so increases
all right so how will I do that right, so
if a is small enough ok, so the best action
will eventually converge to a probability
of 1 if after a is very large I will start
oscillating this will this might not be probabilities
all those problems are the right.
And what about the other case if this is this
if I am doing this, the action some other
action a prime
what should I do for that right, I mean ideally
it should be +a times 0-p so this will work
if it is two actions which multiple actions
what happens, it not be a probability distribution
I will have to make sure that everything stays
probability distribution, where is the multiple
actions have taken away a from everybody then
I should take away a/n-1 from the other actions
okay.
So that when I sum up everything after that
also it will still be 1, starting off with
assumption that pt sums to 1, so I need to
make sure pt+1 also sums to 1, so I will have
to adjust these numbers accordingly okay,
so I am pretty sure all of you can do the
character adjustment, so this is essentially
a one update rule one sec what happens if
I got 0 the reward of 0, this one has nothing
to do with the reward okay.
In fact this one here has nothing to do with
the reward the one here it has to do with
the fact that if the probability I would like
this probability to be one you remember the
form of the rule I told you right, current
value target minus the current value, so the
error right so current value plus a times
error so that is the thing it's the same way
here the probability I want is 0 okay, so
it is the current value+a times 0-p, so I
simplified that I wrote it as 1-a right.
So I'm always writing it in the same stochastic
averaging form right, so the one is the target
I want this not the reward right, so what
i got reward of zero what do, I do to flip
it around right it turns out that well that
is one valid option there are many options
that you can have right, so just look this
around right, I reduce the probability of
the action at took at time T I increase the
probability of faction I took I didn't take
at time T right.
So why do I have to do this just to make sure
it is a probability distribution right when
I reduce this probability this will automatically
have to go up, it is not like I am rewarding
the action I didn't take right, but the fact
we have this constraint of the probabilities
have to sum to 1 we will automatically reward
the other action, okay so but notice i wrote
a and ß, so depending on the relationship
between a and ß.
So you have different kinds of algorithms
right so if a = ß, so we have something called
so they called linear reward penalty LRP algorithm
okay, so it’s this these things have been
around for many many many decades ok, so the
LRP algorithm is a linear because the relationships
there is are linear so you can see there are
no higher order terms in the updates that
you right, so you have you do something you
change the parameters on a reward and you
also change the parameters when you get a
penalty right.
So the reward is +1 penalty is 0 and you are
changing them by equal amounts right, that
is when a = ß, so when a much greater than
ß right, remember these are relative terms
okay, when I say a much greater than ß still
a is very small and I expect a to be like
10-3 or 10-2 or something like that right
even though I write alp a much far greater
than ß that means beta should be 10-5 or
10-7 something much smaller right this is
called
epsilon P.
So I do something when I get a reward right
I do a much much smaller change when I get
a penalty, any idea what the I stands for
yeah, it sets or in action but yeah you get
the idea right so when rewards comes I do
something when the penalty side of it happens
I do nothing, in action I just leave the probabilities
as it is okay and it turns out that there
is very very small change rate the algorithm
itself is the same all I am doing is changing
these things around and it turns out the convergence
behaviors of these three algorithms are very
different right and depending on how how rewarding
your arms are right.
So for example my best arm let us say has
a probability of a binary bandit is 0 or 1
let us say my best arm has a probability of
say 0.9of coming up as one, right and the
other arm has say a probability of 0.6 of
coming up with one, then LRP will work well
right, but suppose my best arm has probability
of 0.3 of coming up of one right and my bad
arm my worst arm has a probability of 0.2
of coming up as one or 0.25 as coming either
one LRP is going to have a hard time infect
it turns out that in such cases LRP works
better because whenever a small reward comes
also you whenever the reward comes right you
keep hiking the probability, because the probability
of getting the reward is so small right.
So if I am doing a something on the penalty
side I always almost always be depressing
my probabilities I will just keep decreasing
the probabilities and increasing the other
probability so there will be a lot of oscillations
right, so in cases where rewards are scarce
to come by its best to ignore the penalties
so there are many many things like this so
yeah, so that is still a very vibrant community
that works with this kind of learning automaton
ideas and this is the most basic most fundamental
of these things I told you about this variable
structure stochastic automata right, as I
asked you about finite state machines and
you all of you said you knows finite state
machines right and I told you then there is
this variable structure finite state machines
as people use for solving.
So these are kind of the culmination of the
variable structure finite state machines right
so you can go down and write it more explicitly
as to how it turns out to be automated right,
but this is more of a compact way of representing
those variables structure finite automata
so I am not going to get into too much detail
even though there is a vibrant community that
does this, right and so this is just to tell
you that this history of using this policy
representations directly right goes back several
decades in fact the earliest such learning
automated method was proposed still the 1930s,
infect these approaches even predate some
of the value function value estimate based
approaches we are talked about okay right.
So fine so we're all on board here so taking
this further now this looks like some kind
of ad hock way of coming up with the policy
updates right, and it seems very natural way
of doing it why I get a reward I increase
the probability ok if I get a penalty I decrease
the probability seems like a very natural
way of doing it but is there a more systematic
way I was thinking about learning the policy
directly right.
.
So very well steady and increasingly a direction
which is receiving a lot of attention call
policy gradient approaches the book calls
these parameterized policy representations,
while the earlier one were you know value
function based methods they call this parameterized
policy approaches, so the basic idea here
is I am going to assume that my policies right,
so here I am giving you the policy has explicit
probability values right.
So I’m going to assume that my policy depends
on
the policy depends on some set of parameters,
so what do I mean by this, so policy is a
probability distribution right I can specify
the probability distribution in many ways
for example I can specify the probability
distribution like we did earlier by a soft
max function right, so if I specified by a
soft max function what is it that I need to
give you in order to define the policy people
remember soft max.
So e power something divided by summation
e power something right, so suppose I am saying
that I need to tell you what the soft max
function is corresponding to my current policy,
right so what is information that I should
communicate to you, so all those exponents
that I am putting in there right for each
action I have something I put in the exponent
I will have to tell you that right, it need
not be values, just remember very much so
I am just talking about the soft max function
right however I derive the value that goes
into the exponent it can be a value function
it can be something else right.
I could have just arbitrarily pulled out some
numbers I could have said action one put a
3 in the exponent ok action two to put a 15
in the exponent action three put a 22 and
the exponent okay this gave you those numbers
arbitrarily but this defines, a policy however
i arrived at those numbers this defines a
policy right, so this is what we call as a
parameterize representation, so i have the
set of parameters ok that defined the policy
for me so I the parameters are somehow used
to generate these numbers for me right.
So this is essentially what we mean by parameters
so we have a set of parameters said there
could be anything there could be those values
that I plug into the exponents which sometimes
are called preferences okay, so that e power
thing right, so I can just say I prefer action
a to action b right and then I can have some
way of converting that into actual probabilities,
and I would say my preference for action is
25 preference for action B is 13 right and
from that I can convert it into probability.
So far because the value has a separate semantic
associated with it right the value is the
expected payoffs that I am going to get on
pulling the arm when I say the preference
for the arm is 23 does not have need necessarily
have any semantics so 23 verses 15 so 23 higher
than 15 there is only semantics I have, right
not necessarily that 23 means that this is
the payoff i am going to get so this gives
me a lot more flexibility and how I change
those values, right. it need not necessarily
come from the estimation of the expectation
okay right.
So it could be preferences it could be say
the weights of a neural network if you have
so inclined, right so this is something which
all of you should be thinking about how many
of you read this article about the go playing
isn't one two therefore five six seven not
enough people everybody go read the go playing
agent about a go go go go go to Google search
for a go it is there in the Hindu for crying
out loud right, anyway.
So this is this machine learning agent which
they do not actually specify exactly what
is the machine learning algorithm that they
use it’s a machine learning agent that learns
to play this game of Go which fora long long
long time was considered one of the hardest
games for computers to play because the number
of patterns that you could have or just huge,
right and rules are very simple but then it
turned out to be a very very hard game for
our computers to play certainly not at human
levels, right but then Google deep mind has
come up as soon as say Google deep mind you
should know what algorithm that they use their
what at least what how they formulated the
problem right.
So they use reinforcement learning and the
deep neural network to train a go agent that
actually beat the European champion 50, I
mean they played a series of five matches
and it beat the champion or all five of them,
right and they are hoping to have a matchup
with the world champion go player, in March
I know that mentioned some dates March yeah
and maybe they still do not hope to beat the
world champion because apparently the world
champion player is at a much higher level
than, the all the other players out there
but still it so that is hope right.
So the point is RL plus neural networks seems
to be the hot thing nowadays right so everybody
wants to do that, right so this is not hesoteric
example if you are going to gout there and
do reinforcement learning this is probably
what you will end up doing right, so where
the parameters would be given by a weights
of a neural network, right and I'll give you
other examples as we go along right so even
this you can think of as a parameter is representation
right okay here is question for you.
So what kind of a probability distribution
are we talking about here, binomial or baronial
no limit depending on whether it is repeated
trials are one trail right, so Bernoulli if
I had multiple actions should have been multinomial
right yeah so binomial multinomial so what
is the equivalent version of Bernoulli, actually
mentioned this in ml plus guys you know whether
the ml should be able to tell them I’m not
talking about the conjugate price verse I
am saying for repeated experiments to outcome
repeated experiments is binomial single trail
is Bernoulli only multiple outcome repeated
experience the ex-experiments is multinomial
single experiment is categorical, okay distribution
called the categorical distribution which
is essentially multiple outcomes single single
experiment probability distributions okay
but anyway.
So what are the parameters that describe binomial
distribution
probability of one or something so that is
essentially that so this is again one way
to think about this is this is also a parameterize
distribution, where I am specifying directly
the parameters of the multinomial or the binomial
in this case I just said a prime i could say
says all a prime not equal to at and then
I have addressed this a then I basically made
it into a multinomial case right.
So this is also parameter thing so I could
specify any kind of distribution like this
right so now what I am going to do is, just
like we did here i am going to modify the
policy parameters directly, right instead
of modified the value functions i will modify
the policy parameters directly what would
be a systematic way of doing this we can come
up with many things right so but I am talking
about gradient based approach.